DEOVRAT PRASAD

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

CONTACT

N/3.30, The Queen Buildings, 5 The Parade, Cardiff CF24 3AA United Kingdom

+44 7514 850 228 deovratd@cardiff.ac.uk https://deovratprasad.github.io/dp/

EDUCATION

PHD • JUNE 2018
PHYSICS AND ASTRONOMY
CSIR Fellow

Indian Institute of Science Bangalore, India Advisor- Prateek Sharma

INTEGRATED M.SC., 2012 PHYSICS

INSPIRE Fellow

Center for Excellence in Basic Sciences, University of Mumbai, India

KEY SKILLS

Physics and Maths
Programming (C, C++, Fortran,
Python, Matlab, MPI)
Handling and developing large
HD/MHD codes
Big Data Analysis
Teaching and mentoring
Excellent communication

INTERESTS

HD/MHD simulations Galaxy evolution modelling Numerical Methods

PROFILE

Astrophysicist with specialisation in numerical modelling of the evolution of galaxies, groups and clusters at low redshifts. Expert in handling large hydrodynamic/ magnetohydrodynamic (HD/MHD) numerical codes and analysis of large data sets. Very strong background in physics and mathematics. Strong ability to collaborate and work in a team environment, design new experiments, and learn and work in new areas.

EXPERIENCE

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCH ASSOCIATE • NOVEMBER 2022 - PRESENT

Physics and Astronomy | Cardiff University | United Kingdom -leading multiple simulation projects studying the evolution of galaxies, groups and clusters at low redshift -publications in leading peer reviewed journals -co-lecturer of PX1228 course for 2022-23 and 2023-24 -guest lecturer for PX4231 course for 2023-24and 2024-25 -co-mentoring a post-graduate student for semester projects

POSTDOCTORAL FELLOW • JULY 2018 - JUNE 2022

Physics and Astronomy | Michigan State University | United States -lead multiple simulation projects studying the evolution of galaxies, groups and clusters projects -multiple publications in leading peer reviewed journals

-mentored undergraduate and graduate students through summer, and semester projects.

ACTIVITIES

- 12 peer reviewed publications in international journals (7 lead author, 5 collaborative)
- -presentation at international conferences, seminars and colloquiums including talks, posters and short videos
- -teaching multiple undergraduate and graduate courses
- -departmental activities like organising focused research group meetings and mentoring students.